Väinämöinen, old and steadfast
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Passed the days of his existence
elelevi aikojansa
Where lie Väinölä's sweet meadows,
noilla Väinölän ahoilla,
Kalevala's extended heathlands:
Kalevalan kankahilla.
There he sang his songs of sweetness
Laulelevi virsiänsä,
Sang his songs and proved his wisdom.
laulelevi, taitelevi.
Day by day he sang unwearied,
Lauloi päivät pääksytysten,
Night by night discoursed unceasing,
yhytysten yöt saneli
Sang the songs of by-gone ages,
muinaisia muisteloita,
Hidden words of ancient wisdom,
noita syntyjä syviä,
Songs which all the children sing not.
joit' ei laula kaikki lapset,
All beyond men's comprehension,
ymmärrä yhet urohot
In these ages of misfortune,
tällä inhalla iällä,
When the race is near Its ending.
katovalla kannikalla.
Far away the news was carried,
Kauas kuuluvi sanoma,
Far abroad was spread the tidings
ulos viestit vierähtävät
Of the songs of Väinämöinen,
Väinämöisen laulannasta,
Of the wisdom of the hero;
urohon osoannasta.
In the south was spread the rumour;
Viestit vierähti suvehen,
Reached to Pohjola the tidings.
sai sanomat Pohjolahan.
Here dwelt youthful Joukahainen,
Olipa nuori Joukahainen,
He, the meagre youth of Lapland;
laiha poika lappalainen.
And, when visiting the village,
Se kävi kylässä kerran;
Wondrous tales he heard related,
kuuli kummia sanoja,
How there dwelt another minstrel,
lauluja laeltavaksi,
And that better songs were carolled.
parempia pantavaksi
Far in Väinölä's sweet meadows,
noilla Väinölän ahoilla,
Kalevala's extended heathlands;
Kalevalan kankahilla,
Better songs than he could compass;
kuin mitä itseki tiesi,
Better than his father taught him.
oli oppinut isolta.
This he heard with great displeasure,
Tuo tuosta kovin pahastui,
And his heart was filled with envy
kaiken aikansa kaehti
That the songs of Väinämöinen
Väinämöistä laulajaksi
Better than his own were reckoned.
paremmaksi itseänsä.
Then he went to seek his mother;
Jo tuli emonsa luoksi,
Sought her out, the aged woman,
luoksi valtavanhempansa.
And declared that he would journey,
Lähteäksensä käkesi,
And was eager to betake him,
tullaksensa toivotteli
Unto Väinölä's far dwellings,
noille Väinölän tuville
That he might contend with Väinö.
kera Väinön voitteloille.
But his father straight forbade him.
Iso kielti poikoansa,
Both his father and his mother,
iso kielti, emo epäsi
Thence to Väinölä to journey,
lähtemästä Väinölähän
That he might contend with Väinö.
kera Väinön voitteloille:
"He will surely sing against you,
"Siellä silma lauletahan,
Sing against you, and will ban you,
lauletahan, lausitahan
Sink your mouth and head in snow-drifts,
suin lumehen, päin vitihin,
And your hands in bitter tempest:
kourin ilmahan kovahan,
Till your hands and feet are stiffened,
käsin kääntymättömäksi,
And incapable of motion."
jaloin liikkumattomaksi."
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"Good the counsel of my father,
"Hyväpä isoni tieto,
And my mother's counsel better;
emoni sitäi parempi,
Best of all my own opinion.
oma tietoni ylinnä.
I will set myself against him,
Jos tahon tasalle panna,
And defy him to a contest,
miesten verroille vetäitä,
I myself my songs will sing him,
itse laulan laulajani,
I myself will speak my mantras;
sanelen sanelijani:
Sing until the best of minstrels
laulan laulajan parahan
Shall become the worst of singers.
pahimmaksi laulajaksi,
Shoes of stone will I provide him,
jalkahan kiviset kengät,
Wooden trousers on his haunches;
puksut puiset lantehille,
On his breast a stony burden,
kiviriipan rinnan päälle,
And a rock upon his shoulders;
kiviharkon hartioille,
Stony gloves his hands shall cover.
kivihintahat kätehen,
And his head a stony helmet."
päähän paatisen kypärän."
Then he went his way unheeding,
Siitä läksi, ei totellut.
Went his way, and fetched his gelding,
Otti ruunansa omansa,
From whose mouth the fire was flashing,
jonka turpa tulta iski,
'Neath whose legs the sparks were flying.
säkeniä säärivarret;
Then the fiery steed he harnessed,
valjasti tulisen ruunan
To the golden sledge he yoked him,
korjan kultaisen etehen.
In the sledge himself he mounted,
Itse istuvi rekehen,
And upon the seat he sat him,
kohennaikse korjahansa,
O'er the horse his whip he brandished,
iski virkkua vitsalla,
With the beaded whip he smote him,
heitti helmiruoskasella.
From the place the horse sprang quickly,
Läksi virkku vieremähän,
And he darted lightly forwards.
hevonen helettämähän.
On he drove with thundering clatter,
Ajoa suhuttelevi.
As he drove a day, a second,
Ajoi päivän, ajoi toisen,
Driving also on the third day,
ajoi kohta kolmannenki.
And at length upon the third day,
Jo päivänä kolmantena
Came to Väinölä's sweet meadows,
päätyi Väinölän ahoille,
Kalevala's extended heathlands.
Kalevalan kankahille.
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen,
He, the oldest of magicians,
tietäjä iän-ikuinen,
As it chanced was driving onward,
oli teittensä ajaja,
Peacefully his course pursuing
matkojensa mittelijä
On through Väinölä's sweet meadows,
noilla Väinölän ahoilla,
Kalevala's extended heathlands.
Kalevalan kankahilla.
Came the youthful Joukahainen
Tuli nuori Joukahainen,
Driving on the road against him,
ajoi tiellä vastatusten:
And the shafts were wedged together,
tarttui aisa aisan päähän,
And the reins were all entangled,
rahe rahkehen takistui,
And the collar jammed with collar,
länget puuttui länkilöihin,
And the runners dashed together.
vemmel vempelen nenähän.
Thus their progress was arrested,
Siitä siinä seisotahan,
Thus they halted and reflected;
seisotahan, mietitähän...
Sweat dropped down upon the runners;
vesi vuoti vempelestä,
From the shafts the steam was rising.
usva aisoista usisi.
Asked the aged Väinämöinen,
Kysyi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Who are you, and what your lineage,
"Kuit' olet sinä sukua,
You who drive so reckless onward,
kun tulit tuhmasti etehen,
Utterly without reflection?
vastahan varattomasti?
Broken are the horses' collars,
Säret länget länkäpuiset,
And the wooden runners likewise;
vesapuiset vempelehet,
You have smashed my sledge to pieces.
korjani pilastehiksi,
Broke the sledge in which I travelled."
rämäksi re'en retukan!"
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Silloin nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"I am youthful Joukahainen;
"Mie olen nuori Joukahainen.
But yourself should also tell me,
Vaan sano oma sukusi:
What your race, and what your nation,
kuit' olet sinä sukua,
And from what vile stock you issue."
kuta, kurja, joukkioa?"
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Told his name without concealment,
jo tuossa nimittelihe.
And began to speak as follows:
Sai siitä sanoneheksi:
"Youth, if you are Joukahainen,
"Kun liet nuori Joukahainen,
You should move aside a little.
veäite syrjähän vähäisen!
For remember, you are younger."
Sie olet nuorempi minua."
But the youthful Joukahainen
Silloin nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Here of youthfulness we reck not;
"Vähä on miehen nuoruuesta,
Nought doth youth or age concern us,
nuoruuesta, vanhuuesta!
He who highest stands in knowledge,
Kumpi on tieolta parempi,
He whose wisdom is the greatest,
muistannalta mahtavampi,
Let him keep the path before him,
sep' on tiellä seisokahan,
And the other yield the passage.
toinen tieltä siirtykähän.
If you are old Väinämöinen,
Lienet vanha Väinämöinen,
And the oldest of the minstrels,
laulaja iän-ikuinen,
Let us give ourselves to singing,
ruvetkamme laulamahan,
Let us now repeat our sayings,
saakamme sanelemahan,
That the one may teach the other.
mies on miestä oppimahan,
And the one surpass the other,"
toinen toista voittamahan!"
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"What can I myself accomplish
"Mitäpä minusta onpi
As a wise man or a singer?
laulajaksi, taitajaksi!
I have passed my life in quiet,
Ain' olen aikani elellyt
Here among these very moorlands,
näillä yksillä ahoilla,
On the borders of my home-field
kotipellon pientarilla
I have heard the cuckoo calling.
kuunnellut kotikäkeä.
But apart from this at present,
Vaan kuitenki kaikitenki
I will ask you to inform me
sano korvin kuullakseni:
What may be your greatest wisdom;
mitä sie enintä tieät,
And the utmost of your knowledge?"
yli muien ymmärtelet?"
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"Many things I know in fulness,
"Tieänpä minä jotaki!
And I know with perfect clearness,
Sen on tieän selvällehen,
And my insight shows me plainly,
tajuelen tarkoillehen:
In the roof we find the smoke-hole,
reppänä on liki lakea,
And the fire is near the hearthstone.
liki lieska kiukoata.
"Joyful life the seal is leading,
"Hyvä on hylkehen eleä,
In the waves there sports the sea-dog,
ve'en koiran viehkuroia:
And he feeds upon the salmon,
luotansa lohia syöpi,
And the powans round about him.
sivultansa siikasia.
"Smooth the water loved by powans,
"Siiall' on sileät pellot,
Smooth the surface, too, for salmon;
lohella laki tasainen.
And in frost the pike is spawning,
Hauki hallalla kutevi,
Slimy fish in wintry weather.
kuolasuu kovalla säällä.
Sluggish is the perch, the humpback,
Ahven arka, kyrmyniska
In the depths it swims in autumn,
sykysyt syvillä uipi,
But it spawns in drought of summer,
kesät kuivilla kutevi,
Swimming slowly to the margin.
rantasilla rapsehtivi.
"If this does not yet suffice you,
"Kun ei tuosta kyllin liene,
I am wise in other matters,
vielä tieän muunki tieon,
And of weighty things can tell you.
arvoan yhen asian:
In the north they plough with reindeer,
pohjola porolla kynti,
In the south the mare is useful,
etelä emähevolla,
And the elk In furthest Lapland.
takalappi tarvahalla.
"Trees I know on Pisa mountain,
Tieän puut Pisan mäellä,
Firs upon the rocks of Horna,
hongat Hornan kalliolla:
Tall the trees on Pisa mountain,
pitkät on puut Pisan mäellä,
And the firs on rocks of Horna.
hongat Hornan kalliolla.
"Three great waterfalls I know of,
"Kolme on koskea kovoa,
And as many lakes extensive,
kolme järveä jaloa,
And as many lofty mountains,
kolme vuorta korkeata
Underneath the vault of heaven.
tämän ilman kannen alla:
Halläpyörä is in Hame,
Hämehess' on Hälläpyörä,
Karjala has Kaatrakoski,
Kaatrakoski Karjalassa;
But they do not match the Vuoksi,
ei ole Vuoksen voittanutta,
There where Imatra is rushing."
yli käynyttä Imatran."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Childish tales, and woman's wisdom,
"Lapsen tieto, naisen muisti,
But for bearded men unsuited,
ei ole partasuun urohon
And for married men unfitted.
eikä miehen naisekkahan!
Tell me words of deepest wisdom.
Sano syntyjä syviä,
Tell me now of things eternal."
asioita ainoisia!"
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Se on nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Well I know whence comes the titmouse,
"Tieän mä tiaisen synnyn,
That the titmouse is a birdie,
tieän linnuksi tiaisen,
And a snake the hissing viper,
kyyn viherän käärmeheksi,
And the ruffe a fish in water.
kiiskisen ve'en kalaksi.
And I know that hard is iron,
Rauan tieän raukeaksi,
And that mud when black is bitter.
mustan mullan muikeaksi,
Painful, too, is boiling water,
varin veen on vaikeaksi,
And the heat of fire is hurtful,
tulen polttaman pahaksi.
Water is the oldest medicine,
"Vesi on vanhin voitehista,
Cataract's foam a magic potion;
kosken kuohu katsehista,
The Creator's self a sorcerer,
itse Luoja loitsijoista,
Jumala the Great Magician.
Jumala parantajista.
"From the rock springs forth the water,
"Vuoresta on vetosen synty,
And the fire from heaven descendeth,
tulen synty taivosesta,
And from ore we get the iron,
alku rauan ruostehesta,
And in hills we find the copper.
vasken kanta kalliosta.
"Marshy country is the oldest,
"Mätäs on märkä maita vanhin,
And the first of trees the willow.
paju puita ensimäinen,
Pine-roots were the oldest houses,
hongan juuri huonehia,
And the earliest pots were stone ones."
paatonen patarania."
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Is there more that you can tell me,
"Muistatko mitä enemmin,
Or is this the end of nonsense?"
vain jo loppuivat lorusi?"
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"Many little things I wot of,
"Muistan vieläki vähäisen!
And the time I well remember
Muistanpa ajan mokoman,
When 'twas I who ploughed the ocean,
kun olin merta kyntämässä,
Hollowed out the depths of ocean,
meren kolkot kuokkimassa,
And I dug the caves for fishes,
kalahauat kaivamassa,
And I sunk the deep abysses,
syänveet syventämässä,
When the lakes I first created,
lampiveet on laskemassa,
And I heaped the hills together.
mäet mylleröittämässä,
And the rocky mountains fashioned.
louhet luomassa kokohon.
"Then I stood with six great heroes!
"Viel' olin miesnä kuuentena,
I myself the seventh among them.
seitsemäntenä urosna
When the earth was first created,
tätä maata saataessa,
And the air above expanded;
ilmoa suettaessa,
For the sky I fixed the pillars.
ilman pieltä pistämässä,
And I reared the arch of heaven,
taivon kaarta kantamassa,
To the moon assigned his journey,
kuuhutta kulettamassa,
Helped the sun upon his pathway,
aurinkoa auttamassa,
To the Bear his place appointed,
otavaa ojentamassa,
And the stars in heaven I scattered,"
taivoa tähittämässä."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Ay, indeed, a shameless liar!
"Sen varsin valehtelitki!
You at least were never present
Ei sinua silloin nähty,
When the ocean first was furrowed,
kun on merta kynnettihin,
And the ocean depths were hollowed.
meren kolkot kuokittihin,
And the caves were dug for fishes,
kalahauat kaivettihin,
And the deep abysses sunken,
syänveet syvennettihin,
And the lakes were first created,
lampiveet on laskettihin,
When the hills were heaped together,
mäet mylleröitettihin,
And the rocky mountains fashioned.
louhet luotihin kokohon.
"No one ever yet had seen you,
"Eikä lie sinua nähty,
None had seen you, none had heard you.
ei lie nähty eikä kuultu
When the earth was first created,
tätä maata saataessa,
And the air above expanded,
ilmoa suettaessa,
When the posts of heaven were planted,
ilman pieltä pistettäissä,
And the arch of heaven exalted,
taivon kaarta kannettaissa,
When the moon was shown his pathway,
kuuhutta kuletettaissa,
And the sun was taught to journey,
aurinkoa autettaissa,
When the Bear was fixed in heaven,
otavaa ojennettaissa,
And the stars in heaven were scattered."
taivoa tähitettäissä."
But the youthful Joukahainen
Se on nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow:
tuosta tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"If I fail in understanding,
"Kun ei lie minulla mieltä,
I will seek it at the sword-point.
kysyn mieltä miekaltani.
O thou aged Väinämöinen,
Oi on vanha Väinämöinen,
O thou very broad-mouthed minstrel,
laulaja laveasuinen!
Let us measure swords together,
Lähe miekan mittelöhön,
Let the blade decide between us."
käypä kalvan katselohon!"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"I have little cause to fret me
"En noita pahoin pelänne
Either for your sword or wisdom,
miekkojasi, mieliäsi,
For your sword-point or your judgment.
tuuriasi, tuumiasi.
But, apart from this at present,
Vaan kuitenki kaikitenki
I will draw no sword upon you,
lähe en miekan mittelöhön
So contemptible a fellow,
sinun kanssasi, katala,
And so pitiful a weakling."
kerallasi, kehno raukka."
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Siinä nuori Joukahainen
Shook his head, his mouth drawn crooked,
murti suuta, väänti päätä,
And he tossed his locks of blackness.
murti mustoa haventa.
And he spake the words which follow:
Itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"He who shuns the sword's decision,
"Ken ei käy miekan mittelöhön,
Nor betakes him to his sword-blade,
lähe ei kalvan katselohon,
To a swine I soon will sing him,
sen minä siaksi laulan,
To a snouted swine transform him.
alakärsäksi asetan.
Heroes I have thus o'erpowered,
Panen semmoiset urohot
Hither will I drive and thither.
sen sikäli, tuon täkäli,
And will pitch them on the dunghill,
sorran sontatunkiohon,
Grunting in the cowshed corner."
läävän nurkkahan nutistan."
Angry then was Väinämöinen,
Siitä suuttui Väinämöinen,
Filled with wrath and indignation,
siitä suuttui ja häpesi.
And himself commenced his singing,
Itse loihe laulamahan,
And to speak his words of wisdom.
sai itse sanelemahan:
But he sang no childish ditties,
ei ole laulut lasten laulut,
Children's songs and women's jesting,
lasten laulut, naisten naurut,
But a song for bearded heroes,
ne on partasuun urohon,
Such as all the children sing not,
joit' ei laula kaikki lapset
Nor a half the boys can master,
eikä pojat puoletkana,
Nor a third can lovers compass,
kolmannetkana kosijat
In the days of dark misfortune,
tällä inhalla iällä,
When our life is near its ending.
katovalla kannikalla.
Sang the aged Väinämöinen;
Lauloi vanha Väinämöinen:
Lakes swelled up, and earth was shaken,
järvet läikkyi, maa järisi,
And the coppery mountains trembled.
vuoret vaskiset vapisi,
And the mighty rocks resounded.
paaet vahvat paukahteli,
And the mountains clove asunder;
kalliot kaheksi lenti,
On the shore the stones were shivered.
kivet rannoilla rakoili.
Then he sang of Joukahainen,
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen:
Changed his runners into saplings,
vesat lauloi vempelehen,
And to willows changed the collar,
pajupehkon länkilöihin,
And the reins he turned to alder,
raiat rahkehen nenähän.
And he sang the sledge all gilded,
Lauloi korjan kultalaian:
To the lake among the rushes,
lauloi lampihin haoiksi;
And the whip, with beads embellished,
lauloi ruoskan helmiletkun
To a reed upon the water,
meren rantaruokosiksi;
And the horse, with front white-spotted
lauloi laukkipään hevosen
To a stone beside the torrent.
kosken rannalle kiviksi.
Then he sang his sword, gold-hilted,
Lauloi miekan kultakahvan
To a lightning-flash in heaven,
salamoiksi taivahalle,
And his ornamented crossbow,
siitä jousen kirjavarren
To a rainbow o'er the water,
kaariksi vesien päälle,
And he sang his feathered arrows,
siitä nuolensa sulitut
Into hawks that soar above him;
havukoiksi kiitäviksi,
And his dog, with upturned muzzle,
siitä koiran koukkuleuan,
Stands a stone in earth embedded.
sen on maahan maakiviksi.
From his head, his cap, by singing,
Lakin lauloi miehen päästä
Next became a cloud above him,
pilven pystypää kokaksi;
From his hands, his gloves, by singing,
lauloi kintahat käestä
Next were changed to water-lilies,
umpilammin lumpehiksi,
And the blue coat he was wearing,
siitä haljakan sinisen
Floats a fleecy cloud in heaven,
hattaroiksi taivahalle,
And the handsome belt that girt him,
vyöltä ussakan utuisen
In the sky as stars he scattered.
halki taivahan tähiksi.
As he sang, sank Joukahainen
Itsen lauloi Joukahaisen:
Waist-deep in the swamp beneath him,
lauloi suohon suonivöistä,
Hip-deep in the marshy meadow,
niittyhyn nivuslihoista,
To his arm-pits in a quicksand.
kankahasen kainaloista.
Then indeed young Joukahainen
Jo nyt nuori Joukahainen
Knew at last, and comprehended;
jopa tiesi jotta tunsi:
And he knew his course was finished,
tiesi tielle tullehensa,
And his journey now was ended.
matkallen osannehensa
For in singing he was beaten,
voittelohon, laulelohon
By the aged Väinämöinen.
kera vanhan Väinämöisen.
He would raise his foot to struggle
Jaksoitteli jalkoansa:
But he could no longer lift it;
eipä jaksa jalka nousta;
Then he tried to lift the other,
toki toistakin yritti:
But as shod with stone he felt it.
siin' oli kivinen kenkä.
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Siitä nuoren Joukahaisen
Felt the greatest pain and anguish,
jopa tuskaksi tulevi,
And he fell in grievous trouble,
läylemmäksi lankeavi.
And he spoke the words which follow:
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"O thou wisest Väinämöinen,
"Oi on viisas Väinämöinen,
O thou oldest of magicians,
tietäjä iän-ikuinen!
Speak thy words of magic backwards,
Pyörrytä pyhät sanasi,
And reverse thy songs of magic.
peräytä lausehesi!
Loose me from this place of terror,
Päästä tästä pälkähästä,
And release me from my torment.
tästä seikasta selitä!
I will pay the highest ransom,
Panenpa parahan makson,
And the fixed reward will give thee."
annan lunnahat lujimmat."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"What do you propose to give me,
"Niin mitä minullen annat,
If I turn my words of magic,
jos pyörrän pyhät sanani,
And reverse my songs of magic,
peräytän lauseheni,
Loose you from this place of terror,
päästän siitä pälkähästä,
And release you from your torment?"
siitä seikasta selitän?"
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"I've two crossbows I could give you,
"Onp' on mulla kaarta kaksi,
Ay, a pair of splendid crossbows,
jousta kaksi kaunokaista;
One shoots forth with passing quickness,
yks' on lyömähän riveä,
Surely hits the mark the other.
toinen tarkka ammunnalle.
If it please you, choose between them."
Ota niistä jompikumpi!"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"No, your bows I do not covet,
"Huoli en, hurja, jousistasi,
For the wretched bows I care not;
en, katala, kaaristasi!
I myself have plenty of them.
On noita itselläniki
All the walls are decked with crossbows,
joka seinä seisoteltu,
All the pegs are hung with crossbows;
joka vaarnanen varottu:
In the woods they wander hunting,
miehittä metsässä käyvät,
Nor a hero needs to span them."
urohitta ulkotöillä."
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen,
In the swamp he sang yet deeper.
lauloi siitäki syvemmä.
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"I have yet two boats to offer;
"Onp' on mulla purtta kaksi,
Splendid boats, as I can witness,
kaksi kaunoista venoa;
One is light, and fit for racing,
yks' on kiistassa kepeä,
Heavy loads will bear the other;
toinen paljo kannattava.
If it please you, choose between them."
Ota niistä jompikumpi!"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"No, your boats I do not covet,
"Enp' on huoli pursistasi,
And I will not choose between them,
venehistäsi valita!
I myself have plenty of them.
On noita itselläniki
All the staves are full already,
joka tela tempaeltu,
Every creek is crowded with them,
joka lahtema laottu,
Boats to face the gale adapted,
mikä tuulella tukeva,
Boats against the wind that travel."
mikä vastasään menijä."
Then the youthful Joukahainen,
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen,
in the swamp he sang yet deeper.
lauloi siitäki syvemmä.
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"I have still two noble stallions;
"On mulla oritta kaksi,
Ay, a pair of handsome horses;
kaksi kaunoista hepoa;
One of these of matchless swiftness,
yks' on juoksulle jalompi,
And the other best in harness.
toinen raisu rahkehille.
If it please you, choose between them."
Ota niistä jompikumpi!"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"No, I do not want your horses;
"En huoli hevosiasi,
Do not need your steeds, white-footed.
sure en sukkajalkojasi!
I myself have plenty of them.
On noita itselläniki
Every stall has now its tenant,
joka soimi solmieltu,
Every stable's filled with horses,
joka tanhua taluttu:
With their backs like water shining;
vesi selvä selkäluilla,
Lakes of fat upon their haunches."
rasvalampi lautasilla."
Then the youthful Joukahainen,
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen,
In the swamp he sang yet deeper.
lauloi siitäki syvemmä.
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"O thou aged Väinämöinen,
"Oi on vanha Väinämöinen!
Speak thy words of magic backwards,
Pyörrytä pyhät sanasi,
And reverse thy songs of magic.
peräytä lausehesi!
I will give a golden helmet,
Annan kultia kypärin,
And a hat filled up with silver,
hope'ita huovan täyen,
Which my father won in warfare,
isoni soasta saamat,
Which he won in battle-struggle."
taluttamat tappelosta."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"No, I do not want your silver,
"En huoli hope'itasi,
And for gold, I only scorn it.
kysy en, kurja, kultiasi!
I myself have both in plenty.
On noita itselläniki
Every storeroom crammed with treasure.
joka aitta ahtaeltu,
Every chest is overflowing.
joka vakkanen varottu:
Gold as ancient as the moonlight,
ne on kullat kuun-ikuiset,
Silver with the sun coeval."
päivän-polviset hopeat."
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen,
In the swamp he sang yet deeper.
lauloi siitäki syvemmä.
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"O thou aged Väinämöinen,
"Oi on vanha Väinämöinen!
Loose me from this place of terror,
Päästä tästä pälkähästä,
And release me from my torment.
tästä seikasta selitä!
All my stacks at home I'll give thee,
Annan aumani kotoiset,
And my fields I likewise promise,
heitän hietapeltoseni
All to save my life I offer,
oman pääni päästimeksi,
If you will accept my ransom."
itseni lunastimeksi."
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"No, your barns I do not covet,
"En halaja aumojasi,
And your fields are 'neath my notice,
herjä, hietapeltojasi!
I myself have plenty of them.
On noita itselläniki,
Fields are mine in all directions,
peltoja joka perällä,
Stocks are reared on every fallow,
aumoja joka aholla.
And my own fields please me better,
Omat on paremmat pellot,
And my stacks of corn are finest."
omat aumat armahammat."
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Lauloi nuoren Joukahaisen,
In the swamp he sang yet deeper.
lauloi ainakin alemma.
Then the youthful Joukahainen,
Siitä nuori Joukahainen
Felt at length the greatest anguish,
toki viimein tuskautui,
Chin-deep in the swamp while sinking,
kun oli leuan liettehessä,
In the mud his beard was draggled,
parran paikassa pahassa,
In the moss his mouth was sunken,
suun on suossa, sammalissa,
And his teeth among the tree-roots.
hampahin haon perässä.
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"O thou wisest Väinämöinen,
"Oi on viisas Väinämöinen,
O thou oldest of magicians,
tietäjä iän-ikuinen!
Sing once more thy songs of magic,
Laula jo laulusi takaisin,
Grant the life of one so wretched,
heitä vielä heikko henki,
And release me from my prison.
laske täältä pois minua!
In the stream my feet are sunken,
Virta jo jalkoa vetävi,
With the sand my eyes are smarting.
hiekka silmiä hiovi.
"Speak thy words of magic backwards,
"Kun pyörrät pyhät sanasi,
Break the spell that overwhelms me!
luovuttelet luottehesi,
You shall have my sister Aino,
annan Aino siskoseni,
I will give my mother's daughter.
lainoan emoni lapsen
She shall dust your chamber for you,
sulle pirtin pyyhkijäksi,
Sweep the flooring with her besom,
lattian lakaisijaksi,
Keep the milk-pots all in order;
hulikkojen huuhtojaksi,
And shall wash your garments for you.
vaippojen viruttajaksi,
Golden fabrics she shall weave you,
kutojaksi kultavaipan,
And shall bake you cakes of honey."
mesileivän leipojaksi."
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Heard his words, and grew full joyful,
ihastui ikihyväksi,
Since to tend his age was promised
kun sai neion Joukahaisen
Joukahainen's lovely sister.
vanhan päivänsä varaksi.
On the stone of joy he sat him,
Istuiksen ilokivelle,
On the stone of song he rested,
laulupaaelle paneikse.
Sang an hour, and sang a second,
Lauloi kotvan, lauloi toisen,
And again he sang a third time:
lauloi kotvan kolmannenki:
Thus reversed his words of magic,
pyörti pois pyhät sanansa,
And dissolved the spell completely.
perin laski lausehensa.
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Pääsi nuori Joukahainen,
From the mud his chin uplifted,
pääsi leuan liettehestä,
And his beard he disentangled,
parran paikasta pahasta,
From the rock his steed led forward,
hevonen kosken kivestä,
Drew his sledge from out the bushes,
reki rannalta haosta,
From the reeds his whip unloosing.
ruoska rannan ruokosesta.
Then upon his sledge he mounted,
Kohoeli korjahansa,
And upon the seat he sat him,
reutoihe rekosehensa;
And with gloomy thoughts he hastened,
läksi mielellä pahalla,
With a heart all sad and doleful,
syämellä synkeällä
Homeward to his dearest mother,
luoksi armahan emonsa,
Unto her, the aged woman.
tykö valtavanhempansa.
On he drove with noise and tumult,
Ajoa karittelevi.
Home he drove in consternation,
Ajoi kummasti kotihin:
And he broke the sledge to pieces,
rikki riihe'en rekensä,
At the door the shafts were broken.
aisat poikki portahasen.
Then the noise alarmed his mother,
Alkoi äiti arvaella,
And his father came and asked him,
isonen sanan sanovi:
"Recklessly the sledge was broken;
"Suottapa rikoit rekesi,
Did you break the shafts on purpose?
tahallasi aisan taitoit!
Wherefore do you drive so rashly,
Mitäpä kummasti kuletki,
And arrive at home so madly?"
tulet tuhmasti kotihin?"
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Tuossa nuori Joukahainen
Could not keep his tears from flowing;
itkeä vetistelevi
Sad he bowed his head in sorrow,
alla päin, pahoilla mielin,
And his cap awry he shifted,
kaiken kallella kypärin
And his lips were dry and stiffened,
sekä huulin hyypynyisin,
O'er his mouth his nose was drooping.
nenän suulle langennuisen.
Then his mother came and asked him
Emo ennätti kysyä,
Wherefore was he sunk in sorrow.
vaivan nähnyt vaaitella:
"O my son, why weep so sadly?
"Mitä itket, poikueni,
O my darling, why so troubled,
nuorna saamani, nureksit,
With thy lips so dry and stiffened,
olet huulin hyypynyisin,
O'er thy mouth thy nose thus drooping?"
nenän suulle langennuisen?"
Said the youthful Joukahainen,
Sanoi nuori Joukahainen:
"O my mother, who hast borne me,
"Oi on maammo, kantajani!
There is cause for what has happened,
Jo on syytä syntynynnä,
For the sorcerer has o'ercome me.
taikoja tapahtununna,
Cause enough have I for weeping,
syytä kyllin itkeäni,
And the sorcerer's brought me sorrow.
taikoja nureksiani!
I myself must weep for ever,
Tuot' itken tämän ikäni,
And must pass my life in mourning,
puhki polveni murehin:
For my very sister Aino,
annoin Aino siskoseni,
She, my dearest mother's daughter,
lupasin emoni lapsen
I have pledged to Väinämöinen,
Väinämöiselle varaksi,
As the consort of the minstrel,
laulajalle puolisoksi,
To support his feeble footsteps,
turvaksi tutisevalle,
And to wait upon him always."
suojaksi sopenkululle."
Joyous clapped her hands his mother,
Emo kahta kämmentänsä
Both her hands she rubbed together,
hykersi molempiansa;
And she spoke the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Do not weep, my son, my dearest,
"Elä itke, poikueni!
For thy tears are quite uncalled for.
Ei ole itkettäviä,
Little cause have we to sorrow,
suuresti surettavia:
For the hope I long have cherished.
tuota toivoin tuon ikäni,
All my lifetime I have wished it,
puhki polveni halasin
And have hoped this high-born hero
sukuhuni suurta miestä,
Might akin to us be reckoned,
rotuhuni rohkeata,
And the minstrel Väinämöinen
vävykseni Väinämöistä,
Might become my daughter's husband."
laulajata langokseni."
But when Joukahainen's sister
Sisar nuoren Joukahaisen
Heard, she wept in deepest sorrow,
itse itkullen apeutui.
Wept one day, and wept a second,
Itki päivän, itki toisen
At the threshold ever weeping,
poikkipuolin portahalla;
Wept in overwhelming sorrow,
itki suuresta surusta,
In the sadness of her spirit.
apeasta miel'alasta.
Then her mother said consoling,
Sai emo sanelemahan:
"Wherefore weep, my little Aino?
"Mitä itket, Ainoseni,
You have gained a valiant bridegroom,
kun olet saava suuren sulhon,
And the home of one most noble,
miehen korkean kotihin
Where you'll look from out the window,
ikkunoillen istujaksi,
Sitting on the bench and talking."
lautsoille lavertajaksi?"
But her daughter heard and answered,
Tuon tytär sanoiksi virkki:
"O my mother who hast borne me,
"Oi emoni, kantajani!
Therefore have I cause for weeping,
Itkenpä minä jotaki:
Weeping for the beauteous tresses,
itken kassan kauneutta,
Now my youthful head adorning,
tukan nuoren tuuheutta,
And my hair so soft and glossy,
hivuksien hienoutta,
Which must now be wholly hidden,
jos ne piennä peitetähän,
While I still am young and blooming.
katetahan kasvavana.
"Then must I through lifetime sorrow
"Tuotapa ikäni itken,
For the splendour of the sunlight,
tuota päivän armautta,
And the moonbeam's charming lustre
suloutta kuun komean,
And the glory of the heavens,
ihanuutta ilman kaiken,
Which I leave, while still so youthful,
jos oisi nuorna jättäminen,
And as child must quite abandon,
lapsena unohtaminen
I must leave my brother's work-room,
veikon veistotanterille,
Just beyond my father's window."
ison ikkunan aloille."
Said the mother to the daughter,
Sanovi emo tytölle,
To the girl the crone made answer,
lausui vanhin lapsellensa:
"Cast away this foolish sorrow,
"Mene, huima, huolinesi,
Cease your weeping, all uncalled for,
epäkelpo, itkuinesi!
Little cause have you for sorrow,
Ei ole syytä synkistyä,
Little cause for lamentation.
aihetta apeutua.
God's bright sun is ever shining
Paistavi Jumalan päivä
On the world in other regions,
muuallaki maailmassa,
Shines on other doors and windows
ei isosi ikkunoilla,
Than your father's or your brother's;
veikkosi veräjän suulla.
Berries grow on every mountain,
Myös on marjoja mäellä,
Strawberries on the plains are growing,
ahomailla mansikoita
You can pluck them in your sorrow
poimia sinun poloisen
Wheresoe'er your steps may lead you;
ilmassa etempänäki,
Not alone on father's acres,
ei aina ison ahoilla,
Or upon your brother's clearings."
veikon viertokankahilla."